Finding Aid for Raymond G. Mullins Papers, 1953-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Raymond G. Mullins Papers 1953-2010 1970-1990
Mullins, Raymond G., 1943-
9919 Aa 2
Ypsilanti, Michigan attorney active in community affairs, particularly in areas of civil rights and minority education. President of National Association for the Advancement of Colored People Ypsilanti-Willow Run Branch, 1981-1982 and 1987 to 1998. Correspondence, papers associated with his involvement in NAACP activities, documents relating to judgeship candidacy in 1992, printed material culled from Martin Luther King, Jr. Day celebrations, and papers documenting service to Brown Chapel A.M.E. Church.
4.75 linear feet in 5 boxes
842 KB online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Raymond G. Mullins (Donor No. 8765 ) in 1998-1999, and in 2012-2013.
The collection is open to research.
Raymond G. Mullins is an attorney and community leader in Ypsilanti, Michigan. He has long been active in numerous civic and professional organizations, including trustee of the Brown Chapel African Methodist Episcopal Church. For two decades, Mullins was instrumental in garnering broad support for the local chapter of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Under his leadership, the Ypsilanti and Willow Run branches merged, memberships more than doubled, the branch opened an office, youth programs thrived, and the organization won several awards at the national level for programming excellence.
Born in Detroit in 1943, Mullins grew up in Ypsilanti. After graduation from Ypsilanti High School, he studied economics and labor law at Howard University, earning a Bachelor of Arts in 1965. From 1966 to 1970, he served as an officer in the United States Air Force. Following honorable discharge, Mullins returned to Michigan to earn a law degree in 1973 at the University of Michigan. Since then he has practiced law in Ypsilanti and was a judicial candidate for the Washtenaw County Circuit Court in 1992.
During the early 1970s, Mullins was a leading force in integrating Perry School, the last segregated school in the city of Ypsilanti, becoming involved with the NAACP soon after opening his law practice in 1974. Active in branch committee work throughout the seventies, including membership, public relations, and education, he brought in new members, raised funds, and increased visibility for the organization by also working at the state level. Mullins served as president from 1981 to 1982 and again from 1987 to 1998. At the heart of his leadership was the belief that NAACP membership should include a cross section of the community -- business leaders, politicians, chamber of commerce members, area ministers. He worked to build a biracial organization and for community-wide response, all but abandoning his law practice after taking the helm. Tackling both controversial and popular issues, Mullins led initiatives in employment and education, stressed the need for children to know and understand their heritage, and encouraged political involvement. It was during his tenure, for example, that advocacy geared toward integrating a previously all-white judiciary in Washtenaw County met with success.
Mullins also built bonds in the community through his participation in Brown Chapel A.M.E. outreach, particularly in promoting and working for the annual Brotherhood Banquet. Originally initiated in 1953, when racial tensions were high, this annual event continues to bring people from across the region together to rededicate themselves to the cause of racial and religious goodwill and tolerance. In 1991 at that event, Mullins received the Service Award from Brown Chapel. The prior year he was named Man of the Year by Detroit's Minority Women's Network and won the Community Involvement Award from the Ypsilanti Chamber of Commerce.
Although Mullins retired from the presidency of NAACP in 1998, he continues to carry on a family tradition of community involvement, even as he directs more of his energy toward his law practice. Both of his parents believed it was important to give something back to the community. In that tradition, and in their honor, Mullins established the Glenn and Laura L. Mullins Community Foundation, designed to advance educational opportunities for minority students.
The Raymond G. Mullins papers are mainly comprised of National Association for the Advancement of Colored People material; papers related to his Washtenaw judgeship candidacy in 1992; printed material from Martin Luther King Day celebrations; and documents representing his years of service to Brown Chapel African Methodist Episcopal Church. The 4.75 linear feet collection covers the years 1953 to 2010 and are arranged into the following series:
Political and Professional Activities
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People
Brown Chapel African Methodist Episcopal Church
Organization Affiliations
Subjects:
Mullins, Raymond G., 1943-; African Americans--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Civil rights--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Ypsilanti-Willow Run Branch.; Brown Chapel African Methodist Episcopal Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Race relations.; African Americans--Civil rights.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Mullins, Raymond G., 1943-; Ali, Muhammad, 1942-; Riegle, Donald W., 1938-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal and Political
  The Political and Professional series (1.5 linear feet) includes biographical material such as resumes and newspaper articles about Mullins, material documenting his 1992 judgeship candidacy, and correspondence. Also part of this series are several files covering the Fulton Eaglin campaign in 1994 to succeed William Ford in Congress. (Eaglin lost in the primary to Lynn Rivers.)
  Researchers interested in his legal career will find the candidacy files of interest, particularly the photocopy of the completed State Bar of Michigan questionnaire and the letters of support. There are also folders concerning legal organizations Mullins was involved in, including the Vanzetti M. Hamilton Bar Association, Washtenaw County Bar Association, Washtenaw County Black Bar Association, and the Ypsilanti Bar Association. Another item of interest involving Mullin's legal career is the By-Laws and stock certificate of his practice. Finally, the series includes Mullin's Business Expansion Plan.
  The series also contains a section entitled "Personalities" which is organized by the name of the person Mullins associated with and/or about whom he collected information. These files primarily contain newspaper clippings; however some also include correspondence, resumes, event invitations, and biographical information. For example, the folder for Congressman Bill Ford contains correspondence between Ford and Mullins, along with invitations to events. Many of the people included are figures in the Ypsilanti community. Others are state and national figures. Of particular interest are autographed collectors cards of Muhammad Ali. Together, these files create a profile of contemporaries that may have influenced Mullin's work.
  The miscellaneous folder contains President Shelton's (of Eastern Michigan University) remarks at a 1992 Board of Regents meeting. It also contains a newsletter of the Unity Church of Inkster and Mullin's nomination for the Martin Luther King I Have a Dream Award.
  - Biographical Data (Box 1)
    (resumes, newspaper articles, applications for law experiences)
  - Candidacy: Washtenaw County Judgeship 1992 (Box 1)
  - Community Awards 1999 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1990s (Box 1)
  - Fulton Eaglin Campaign 1994
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Issues (Box 1)
    - Notes (Box 1)
    - Personalities (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Legal Committee Work 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper articles 1999-2000 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries 1953-1992 (Box 1)
    (includes tribute to Laura Mullins)
  - By-Laws of Raymond G. Mullins Attorney at Law P.C. and stock certificate (Box 1)
  - Committee on the Judiciary (Box 1)
  - Committee to Retain Justice Mallett (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1980s-1990s, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Court cases (Box 1)
  - Expansion business plan (Box 5)
  - Letter to the Editor (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Newspaper clippings, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Personalities
    (collected material)
    - Adams, Charles G. (Box 5)
    - Ali, Muhammad (Box 5)
    - Allen, Janet (Box 5)
    - Anderson, N. Charles (Box 5)
    - Anthony, Wendell (Box 5)
    - Archer, Dennis (Box 5)
    - Ashe, Arthur (Box 5)
    - Bailey, Tekeshia (Box 5)
    - Ball, Eric (Box 5)
    - Barfield, John (Box 5)
    - Barron, Wendell (Box 5)
    - Beatty, Charles (Box 5)
    - Braun, Carol Moseley (Box 5)
    - Breyer, Stephen (Box 5)
    - Brown, Kenneth (Box 5)
    - Brown, Shirley (Box 5)
    - Brown, Tony (Box 5)
    - Bullard, Perry (Box 5)
    - Burton, John (Box 5)
    - Campbell, Ross W. (Box 5)
    - Chandler, Patsy (Box 5)
    - Chavis, Benjamin (Box 5)
    - Clinton, Bill (Box 5)
    - Cleveland, Clyde (Box 5)
    - Collins, Barbara-Rose (Box 5)
    - Collins, John B. (Box 5)
    - Conlin, Patrick J. (Box 5)
    - Connors, Timothy (Box 5)
    - Conyers Jr., John (Box 5)
    - Cooper, Ron (Box 5)
    - Cosby, Bill (Box 5)
    - Cress, George (Box 5)
    - Crockett, George (Box 5)
    - Davis, Fred (Box 5)
    - Drain, Gershwin (Box 5)
    - Duderstadt, James J. (Box 5)
    - Dukes, Joseph (Box 5)
    - Elders, Joycelyn (Box 5)
    - Engler, John (Box 5)
    - Evers-Williams, Myrlie (Box 5)
    - Farrakhan, Louis (Box 5)
    - Ferguson, Joel (Box 5)
    - Fink, Karl (Box 5)
    - Foley, Mary L. (Box 5)
    - Ford, Bill, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Francis, Nancy C. (Box 5)
    - Fuller, A. Oveta (Box 5)
    - Fulton, John (Box 5)
    - Gilsdorf, Herbert (Box 5)
    - Goodman, George (Box 5)
    - Grimes, Ralph W. (Box 5)
    - Guinier, Lani (Box 5)
    - Haller, Donald T. (Box 5)
    - Hatter, Jerry (Box 5)
    - Higginbotham Jr., A. Leon (Box 5)
    - Hocks, Benjamin (Box 5)
    - Howard-Pritchett, Ethel (Box 5)
    - Jackson, Jesse (Box 5)
    - Joiner, Charles (Box 5)
    - Jones, James Earl (Box 5)
    - Keith, Damon T. (Box 5)
    - Kirkendall, John (Box 5)
    - LaPlata, George (Box 5)
    - Levin, Carl (Box 5)
    - Lightfoot, Albert (Box 5)
    - Logan, Benjamin (Box 5)
    - Mackie, Brian (Box 5)
    - Malcolm X (Box 5)
    - Mallett, Conrad (Box 5)
    - Marable, Manning (Box 5)
    - Marshall, Albert P. (Box 5)
    - Marshall, Thurgood (Box 5)
    - Mattson, Ann (Box 5)
    - McKeown, L.J. (Box 5)
    - Mfume, Kweisi (Box 5)
    - Monaghan, Thomas (Box 5)
    - Moorman, Ruth (Box 5)
    - Morris, Melinda (Box 5)
    - Morrison, Toni (Box 5)
    - Murdock, Peter (Box 5)
    - Newton, Sharon (Box 5)
    - Nicholas, Denise (Box 5)
    - Parks, Rosa (Box 5)
    - Patrick, Deval (Box 5)
    - Perot, Ross (Box 5)
    - Perry, Lowell (Box 5)
    - Person-Brown, Dr. Deloisteen (Box 5)
    - Peterson, Ronnie (Box 5)
    - Pollack, Lana (Box 5)
    - Porter, John (Box 5)
    - Powell, Lloyd (Box 5)
    - Profit, Kirk (Box 5)
    - Quayle, Dan (Box 5)
    - Reynolds, Nanette (Box 5)
    - Richendollar, James (Box 5)
    - Riegle Jr., Donald W. (Box 5)
    - Shea, Thomas (Box 5)
    - Shelton, Donald (Box 5)
    - Simpson, O.J. (Box 5)
    - Smith, Alma (Box 5)
    - Stephens, Cynthia (Box 5)
    - Strong, Jerome (Box 5)
    - Stumbo, Brenda (Box 5)
    - Tanter, Raymond (Box 5)
    - Thomas, Clarence (Box 5)
    - Turner, Tom (Box 5)
    - Widgeon, Betty (Box 5)
    - Wilder, Kurtis (Box 5)
    - Williams, Harry (Box 5)
    - Williams, LaRon (Box 5)
    - Wolpe, Howard (Box 5)
    - Woods, Ronald (Box 5)
    - Yomtoob, Youssef "Joe" (Box 5)
    - Yuille, Levon (Box 5)
    - Zuhlke, David (Box 5)
  - Report on practice (Box 5)
  - Vanzetti M. Hamilton Bar Association (Box 5)
  - Washtenaw County Bar Association (Box 5)
  - Washtenaw County Black Bar Association (Box 5)
  - Washtenaw County Board of Commissioners (Box 5)
  - Ways and Means Committee (Box 5)
  - Yes Michigan! Yes Willow Run! (General Motors Willow Run Assembly Plant) (Box 5)
  - Ypsilanti Bar Association (Box 5)
- National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Ypsilanti-Willow Run Branch
  The National Association for the Advancement of Colored People series is mainly comprised of NAACP papers and clippings dating from 1974 to 1992. (Photocopied material includes some earlier dates.) Documents in folders Mullins labeled "Memorabilia" include education committee papers regarding desegregation in Ypsilanti schools, state conference activities, news clippings and an occasional copy of meeting minutes. Also of note is a folder with a brief historical sketch and photocopied articles on the history of the organization. Among the later is a July 1919 reprint from Crisis Magazine which discussed NAACP recruiting in the midwest. Ypsilanti experiences are featured, along with Detroit, Cleveland, and other industrial cities. The series also holds letters to Congressman William Ford urging that a national holiday be declared to honor Martin Luther King, Jr. and a collection of programs and clippings from Martin Luther King, Jr. Day celebrations. The photographs are of Mullins with Muhammad Ali in 1992 and Don Riegle in 1993, both autographed.
  - History Notes (Box 1)
  - Martin Luther King Day 1985-1996, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia 1974-1982, 1988, 1992, 1995, 1998, 2000-2001, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1976, 1985, 1990-2001 (Box 1)
  - Photographs 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    (Muhammed Ali, Don Rieglie)
  - Million Man March, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Freedom Fund Dinner 1991, 1993, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Freedom Fund and Scholarship Dinner 1999 (Box 1)
  - Freedom Fund Reception 1999 (Box 1)
  - Freedom Fund Banquet 2000-2002 (Box 1)
  - Local branches
    - Ann Arbor 2001 (Box 1)
    - Western Wayne County 2000 (Box 1)
- Brown Chapel African Methodist Episcopal Church
  The National Association for the Advancement of Colored People series (1.5 linear feet and 842 KB) is comprised mainly of events that they organized and meeting materials. Documents in folders Mullins labeled "Memorabilia" include education committee papers regarding desegregation in Ypsilanti schools, state conference activities, news clippings and an occasional copy of meeting minutes. Also of note is a folder with a brief historical sketch and photocopied articles on the history of the organization. Among the later is a July 1919 reprint from Crisis Magazine which discussed NAACP recruiting in the Midwest. Ypsilanti experiences are featured, along with Detroit, Cleveland, and other industrial cities. The series also holds letters to Congressman William Ford urging that a national holiday be declared to honor Martin Luther King, Jr. and a collection of programs and clippings from Martin Luther King, Jr. Day celebrations. The photographs are of Mullins with Muhammad Ali in 1992 and Don Rieglie in 1993, both autographed.
  The series also contains materials of the Afro-Academic, Cultural, Technological, Scientific Olympics (ACT-So) competition. There are balance sheets, correspondence, fliers, grant applications, a news article, and programs about the event. Events that have limited material, including the Radioathon and C. Eugene Beatty Golf Classic, are included in the "miscellaneous events" folder. The individual event folders contain correspondence about the event, fliers, and meeting minutes.
  A folder that may hold particular interest is the "officer elections" folder, which includes a list of officers for election in 1994 and nomination forms from the 1990 election.
  A significant portion of the collection is comprised of meeting materials. In order to maintain the original order of the collection, the executive and general membership meetings have been grouped together. Meeting materials include notes, agendas, minutes, brochures, reports (treasurer, finance, and presidential reports), and sign in sheets. Assuming that they were distributed during meetings, fliers and brochures were kept in their original order and filed with the meeting materials.
  Another large part of the series is membership information and includes membership lists from different committees and years.
  - History Notes (Box 1)
  - Martin Luther King Day 1985-1996, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia 1974-1982, 1988, 1992, 1995, 1998, 2000-2001, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1970s-2001 (Box 1)
  - Photographs 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Million Man March, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Freedom Fund Banquet 2000-2002 (Box 1)
  - Freedom Fund Committee (Box 1)
  - Freedom Fund Dinner 1991, 1993, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Freedom Fund and Scholarship Dinner 1999 (Box 1)
  - Freedom Fund Reception 1999 (Box 1)
  - Local branches
    - Ann Arbor 2001 (Box 1)
    - Western Wayne County 2000 (Box 1)
  - Adopted Calendar of Events 1993, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Afro-Academic, Cultural, Technological, Scientific Olympics (ACT-SO)
    - Balance sheet 2003 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1997 (Box 3)
    - Fliers 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Grant applications (Box 3)
    - News article 1995 (Box 3)
    - Programs 1995-2003 (Box 3)
  - Agreement between Michigan Department of Public Health and NAACP 1991 (Box 3)
  - Annual Conventions 1994-1996 (Box 3)
  - Annual Finance Report Summary 2000 (Box 3)
  - Armed Services and Veterans Affairs Information Bulletins (Box 3)
  - Black History Month Program 2004-2005 (Box 3)
  - Budgets 1991-1995 (Box 3)
  - Cabaret 1995 (Box 3)
  - Coloring book (Box 3)
  - Constitutions and By-Laws (Box 3)
  - Education Forum agenda 1994 (Box 3)
  - Financial Policies/Procedures (Western Wayne County Branch) (Box 3)
  - Judge Clarence Thomas nomination 1991 (Box 3)
  - List of committees for year 1995-1996 (Box 3)
  - Meeting materials 1990-2004 (Box 3)
    folders 1 through 7
  - Meeting materials 1990-2004 (Box 4)
    folders 8 through 11
  - Meeting materials 2001, .ZIP file
    (Executive and General Membership meeting minutes from July 2001 for the Ypsilanti-Willow Run Branch of the NAACP, along with a list of those holding life memberships in the organization.)
  - Membership information
    - Executive Committee 1995-1996 (Box 4)
    - Life Membership File 1994 (Box 4)
    - MBO 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - Roster Report 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Roster Report 2003-2004 (Box 4)
    - Membership Summary Report 2002 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Mobilizer 1995 (Box 4)
  - Midwest Region III Training Conference (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous events (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous materials related to the 'Fight for Freedom' banquet and Midwest Region III Training Conference 2000-2001, 2000-2001, .ZIP file
    (Promotional materials for the 'Fight for Freedom' banquet hosted by the Ypsilanti-Willow Run Branch of the NAACP on October 14, 2000, along with notes from the 2001 Midwest Region III Training Conference.)
  - National organization publications, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - News release 1993 (Box 4)
  - Officer elections (Box 4)
  - Petitions (Box 4)
  - Ray Mullins Thank You Event (Box 4)
  - Requests from students for funding (Box 4)
  - Resolutions 1995 (Box 4)
  - "Salt of the Earth" Family Project (Box 4)
  - Teen Violence Project (Box 4)
  - Veterans Community Working Group (Box 4)
  - Washington Coalition (March in Washington D.C.) (Box 4)
- Organization Affiliations
  The Organization Affiliations series (0.75 linear feet) includes papers, newspaper clippings, and publications from the many organizations Mullins was active in. Organizations include religious, political, legal, and community groups, with an emphasis on African American groups. Mullins was involved with local fraternities and sororities, including Omega Psi Phi, Sigma Rho Chapter and Alpha Kappa Alpha, Delta Psi Omega Chapter. There are folders in the series that contain fliers of events Mullins participated in and attended that were held by these organizations.
  The series also contains information on Loyal Opposition to the Status Quo, of which Mullins was the President and founder. This section contains an article written by Mullins, an agenda, history of the organization, budget, calendar, and a member list.
  The Miscellaneous community events and organizations folders contain brochures and programs of multiple events and organizations. Mullins relationships with these organizations are unknown. However, these organizations may have been affiliated with his own in some way since many of them concern social issues in Washtenaw County.
  Finally, the series contains correspondence, an organizational chart, fliers, and minutes of the Glenn and Laura L. Mullins Community Foundation, Inc. Mullins served as the President of this organization.
  - African American Development Institute 1989-1991 (Box 2)
  - African American Organizations 1981-1988 (Box 2)
  - African Methodist Episcopal Churches, Michigan 1986-1995 with gaps (Box 2)
  - African Methodist Episcopal Churches, outside Michigan 1991-1994 (Box 2)
  - Baptist Churches 1990-1999 (Box 2)
    (includes Task Force on Historic Preservation)
  - Baptist: Huron Valley Missionary Baptist Association (Box 2)
  - Baptist: Local Black Ministers 1981-1985, 1992-1995 (Box 2)
  - Black History Month 1980-1990, 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - Black Law Student Association 1975-1990 (Box 2)
  - Christian Groups 1975, 1989, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1972, 1982, 1990-1993 (Box 2)
    (appreciation for participation in events)
  - Democratic Party 1986-1993 (Box 2)
  - Fair Housing Center of Washtenaw County 1990-1999 (Box 2)
  - Fraternities and sororities
    - Alpha Kappa Alpha, Delta Psi Omega Chapter (Box 2)
    - Omega Psi Phi, Kappa Alpha Psi (Box 2)
    - Omega Psi Phi, Sigma Rho Chapter (Box 2)
  - Glenn and Laura L. Mullins Community Foundation 1998-2000 (Box 2)
  - Greater Ypsilanti Leadership Council, 1995-1996. (Box 2)
  - Guardians of Washtenaw County 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    (police relations)
  - Law Associations 1986-1987, 1991-1996 (Box 2)
  - Literature: African Americans and the Justice System 1974-1975, 1992, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Literature: Discrimination 1994, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Loyal Opposition to the Status Quo, Inc. (LOSQ) 2008-2012 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Association of Black Social Workers 1979, 1990 (Box 2)
  - The Minister's Alliance of Ypsilanti, Ann Arbor & Vicinity 1990-1992 (Box 2)
  - Minority Business Owners 1980, 1986, 1999 (Box 2)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Inc. 2001 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Articles by Mullins 1996 (Box 2)
  - Universities 1980-1990 (Box 2)
  - Operation G.I.T. 1976 (Box 2)
    (Get it Together)
  - Washtenaw County Community Action Agency 1998 (Box 2)
  - Youth Associations 1970, 1992-1993, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Fair Housing Center of Washtenaw County (Box 4)
  - Million Man March Association of Washtenaw County (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous community events and organizations, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Operation Education Classic (Box 4)
  - People-Organizing-Working-Evolving-Reaching (P.O.W.E.R.) Annual Report (1999) and Articles of Incorporation (Box 4)
  - United Youth on the Move, Straight Up newsletter (Box 4)
Related material
The National Association for the Advancement of Colored People Ypsilanti-Willow Run Branch Records, 1918 and 1977-1998 (bulk 1989-1998) held by the Bentley Historical Library.